a few weeks back i took part in mech jam
3 where i created not only my first
tactics game but also my first fully 3d
game in godot lmx and in this video i'm
going to break down how i managed to
pull this off including details on art
creation design considerations project
structure and system design since i
figured the game dev world could use
more info on how these systems based
games are made not saying that i've done
everything right because i definitely
have not but just sharing what did and
did not work for me and what my
takeaways are for future projects that
maybe will spark some ideas for you as
well
so real quick what is lmx it is a
turn-based tactical combat game where
you control mechs that can control one
of three elements fire water and
lightning as you'd expect from a game
involving the elements there are also
interactions between elements water puts
out fire but makes lightning stronger
for instance and fire burns enemies over
several turns but can also be used to
burn trees and therefore carve new paths
through the levels i wanted to go a lot
further with this concept of elemental
interactions including letting mecs
merge together to create new elements
such as fire plus water mech equals
steam mech but as is always the case
with game jams i had to cut scope pretty
aggressively and just settle on the
foundational concept of elemental mechs
which really are the main hook here
anyways and as i mentioned before this
was my first tactics game so i kind of
had to stick to some pretty standard
tactics stuff for the rest of the game
so there's a square grid one team goes
after the other and acting before moving
ends your turn early and so on if you've
played any sort of tactics game before
like fire emblem into the breach and so
on then you're going to be comfortable
with lmx
so with that out of the way let's talk
about how this game was actually made
i'm going to start out by talking about
artwork and i may do a more in-depth
look at this process in a future video
but since i wanted to do the artwork
myself and i can't really draw isometric
very well i decided to go 3d but with
some massive assists to make this
feasible and the time available so all
assets in the game are made with asset
forge which is an offering by the one
and only kinney where you can take
pre-designed blocks and piece them
together to make new and interesting
designs you're obviously limited to
kenny's unique style of low poly artwork
but if you're okay with that and i
personally am then this is an incredibly
fast way to make 3d art furthermore
since i had to keep scope minimal i
decided to just make one mech model and
recolor it for the different unit types
simple and effective after modeling
comes rigging and animation which at
first i thought i might try to do myself
since i know just enough blender to be
dangerous but after spending an hour or
so with mediocre results i decided to
just go with my planned alternative of
using miximo mixamo isn't exactly a
secret in the gamedev world but it's
absolutely worth trying out if you have
humanoid characters you want to rig an
animate you just take your model drop a
few points onto it so that the app knows
where the different parts of the body
are and you end up with a fully rigged
character ready to be animated either by
yourself or by using the large library
of animations that miximo offers oh and
all of this is free by the way the main
downside to mixamo other than being
stuck with their library of animations
is that it doesn't let you download
multiple animations in one file meaning
even on a small project like mine with
only one mech to animate i had to
download over 10 files and then merge
them myself there's a few different ways
to do this including websites blender
tutorials and so on but i just did it
all in godot since you can copy and
paste animations from one file to
another and speaking of godot as
mentioned above this is my first proper
3d game in godot i'm not completely new
to the process as i have done some 3d
prototypes in the past but there was
still a lot to figure out and as many
are aware the default 3d environment in
godot is pretty mediocre so i went with
the guidance from this youtube video by
tocus and games to help create a vibrant
colorful game and then adjust it from
there i still had to do some odd color
and material tweaks to get the models
looking how i wanted to between asset
forge and godot i'm gonna chalk that up
more to my own inexperience with
lighting and materials and so on and at
least editing materials in godot is easy
enough
so now let's look at how i structured
the code of the application because
there is a lot going on in even a basic
tactics game like this and while i think
i got the general idea right there's
definitely room for improvement here so
let's start out with the mechs which all
share the same base entity and then
apply their own customizations on top of
it each mac consists of the model
animations which are all stored in an
animation player node some particle
effects and a state machine which
usually just watches for an animation to
finish and tells the parent entity we
are done doing something though the
movement state also determines the route
to the target destination and moves
along that route at the desired speed
for instance all of the mid-state
triggers such as when to play a sound
effect or when to deal damage when an
attack lands are fired in the animation
for that state which had the really cool
side effect of letting me put an
animation speed setting in the game so
that you can speed up the rate of play
this setting basically just increases
movement speed and changes the playback
speed property of the animation player
node and everything else just works the
list of actions that each met can take
is a simple resource that really just
acts as a container of actions and it
probably could have even just been kept
simpler as an array since i don't need
persistence throughout the application
and while i did have some additional
uses in mind originally for what this
list could do
that ended up not happening
actions themselves also extend the
resource class and consist of a list of
effects and some metadata about the
action such as its name in the ui what
method it should be using for selecting
a target such as a single cell versus a
line of sight and so on
effects are what actually define what an
action does each effect defines a single
aspect of an action such as a state
change a function call or even just
dealing damage to a target with a
collection of effects on an action we
can therefore have actions with unique
abilities a typical attack action for
instance might consist of a planning
effect to let us know that the user ai
needs to first select a target followed
by a change state effect to trigger the
attack animation which as mentioned
previously will trigger the actual
damage resolution once the animation is
at the point where an attack would land
on the target but it does use a damage
effect to know how much damage to deal i
will say that overall while i liked this
system pretty well i did find using
resources for every effect to be a pain
since i have to duplicate each instance
of the effect so that i could have
effect a do a different amount of damage
than effect b so i don't know if i'd go
with this method again i think i prefer
what i've done on kaiju clash where i
define some basic data container classes
in code using the reference class and
then instantiate them at runtime to
define what an attack does it's not
quite as pretty or convenient as editing
things in the editor but it does mean i
don't have to remember to click make
unique in the editor when i'm editing a
resource food for thought on trade-offs
at the very least
so now that we have our actions set up
how do they actually work in practice
well first we select our action to take
either from the ui for player controlled
mix or as decided by the ai node on
every mech more on that later once an
action is selected it goes to an action
resolver node which handles actually
parsing out the effects of an action and
figuring out how to execute it the
repair action for instance plays the
repair animation and heals the mech
which is pretty straightforward and
simple to resolve but most actions
require an additional planning stage
before execution where are you moving to
what target do you want to attack etc if
the mech is player controlled we signal
that we need the player to decide a
target if the mech is ai controlled we
already know our target since that was
taken into account during the decision
making process either way once the
target has been selected we let the
resolver know to continue resolving the
action and go through all effects
changing states calling functions etc
until they've all been resolved once
this is complete we signal that the mech
has completed its turn and that the game
should go on to the next mech with the
systems and design of actions out of the
way we can now take a quick game design
detour to talk about the attacks
themselves and how everything is
balanced to provide an interesting
challenge to the player initially each
mech was going to have the move and
repair actions along with two element
specific attacks after a few days of
development though it became clear that
doing two unique attacks per mech would
take too much time to implement
imbalance and that my time was better
spent elsewhere so every mech in the
game shares the repek move and punch
actions and then has a unique ranged
attack the punch attack is strong but
requires the attacking mech to be
adjacent to the target the unique
attacks are as follows
enemy mechs have a pistol attack that is
weak but has a long range fire mechs
have a short range flamethrower attack
that deals medium damage but also deals
burn damage to mex over time and can be
used to clear foliage water mechs have a
weak medium range attack that boosts
lightning damage and lightning mechs
have a long range medium strength attack
that becomes extremely powerful when
combined with water with everything
listed out like that and keeping in mind
that all mechs have identical stats it
becomes pretty clear how the attacks are
balanced generally speaking attacks get
weaker the larger their ranges with the
exception of lightning attacks which
always do at least a moderate amount of
damage the trade-off on lightning
attacks though is that since they are
most powerful when combined with water
attacks and since the water attack on
its own is really weak there's a strong
opportunity cost to not using a
lightning attack on a mech that is wet
i'm not gonna claim that the attacks are
perfectly balanced or that no attack in
the game couldn't do more or less damage
and be better but the general concept of
trading range for strength with the
exception of attacks that are dependent
on one another for max damage is pretty
sound i think so with actions out of the
way let's now step up a bit higher in
the application hierarchy and talk about
turn order and execution combat is
managed at three different levels a
combat manager for lack of a better word
here i just refer to as combatants in my
code two combatant groups for the player
and enemy mechs and then the mechs
themselves inside of whichever group
they belong to the combatant manager is
focused on really high level management
of the mechs and groups for instance
when a level starts the combatant
manager loads in the data from the level
editor and spawns mechs into the correct
combatant groups and locations it also
does a bit of dependency injection so
that it can be signaled for various
events by combatant groups such as when
a turn has been completed or if all
mechs in that group are dead and it also
adds a few helper functions to the
combatant groups after that it largely
just waits to be notified of when a turn
has ended and signals to the opposite
combatant group that it may begin taking
its turn combatant groups manage the
individual mechs belonging to either the
enemy or the player team these groups do
things like cycle through the available
mechs to make sure everyone has taken an
action before marking the group's turn
as complete letting the individual mechs
know when it's their turn to take an
action and monitor overall team health
so we can let the combatant manager know
when a level has been won or lost the
groups don't handle a whole lot of code
but what they do is pretty integral to
the operation of the game
so as i mentioned above i load in mech
data from a level editor so you may be
wondering what that editor actually
looks like in short the levels
themselves and the editor are both just
made of grid maps that i edit in the
editor there's one grid map for the
basic ground and water tiles though the
actual water effect is just a simple
partially transparent plane there's one
grid map to define the spawn locations
of the mechs and then there's another
grid map for foliage in retrospect
though i should have just done level
design on a simple 2d tile map and then
rendered that data into the grid maps as
it would have been simpler and faster to
work with plus godot doesn't seem to
like having multiple grid maps being
edited in the scene as i'd occasionally
get an error about certain signals
already existing and not able to be
connected and this was usually followed
by some general weirdness in the grid
maps like a tile from the ground grid
map appearing in the foliage grid map
and i'd have to restart the editor to
fix this despite being an imperfect
solution though it did still work quite
well as i was able to put more levels
into the game than i was expecting and
since the levels are composed of grid
maps that also made it easy to load data
into godot's built-in a-star 2d library
to build out pathfinding why use a star
2d instead of the 3d variant since this
is a 3d game well simply put there's no
verticality in this game so there's no
need to have the vertical access as part
of the pathfinding process this is
especially useful since not everything
is on the same plane anyways foliage for
instance sits on top of the ground but
should still act as an obstacle for
pathfinding purposes dropping the y-axis
from pathfinding makes this
automatically get taken into account
since we don't have to worry about what
height an object is at just whether or
not it should be blocking the way
so now that we've talked levels let's
take another game design break and talk
about how the levels were actually
designed this being my first tactics
game i can't say that this is something
i'm well attuned to and there's
definitely a lot of room for improvement
with this game so to try to figure this
out in a time efficient manner i tried
to fall back on the core concept behind
a lot of great game design decisions and
that is giving the player meaningful
choices tactics games are natural fits
for providing the player with options
and letting them decide what path to
take especially when you throw in a
thinking and reactionary opponent who is
working towards an opposing goal so in
lmx a lot of the time it comes down to
which targets do you attack first which
ones do you try to avoid and how
flexible is your strategy do you try and
funnel enemies through a choke point but
risk being slowly beaten down by ranged
attacks or do you split the team and try
to take on all the enemies at once but
risk being defeated in a one-on-one
encounter do you always keep water and
lightning mechs together to do maximum
damage or do you split them up and do
less optimal damage to maybe try and
keep a fire mech alive i think the level
surrounded which is coincidentally also
the hardest level in the game is the
level that best shows what i was going
for with my level design in this level
you start out with a fire water and
lightning mech in the middle of the map
two enemy mechs are nearby but don't
have a direct path to the player and two
enemy mechs are further off but their
path forward is more clear do you go
ahead and attack the mechs that are
nearby if so the fire mech risk opening
up a more direct path for that enemy to
take do you move to one side of the map
and engage in combat earlier or stay in
the middle staying in the middle buys
you the most time but it leaves you
exposed to range attacks for several
turns and will eventually lead to all
four mechs surrounding you and doing
some serious damage it's choices like
these i wanted to offer some levels like
surrounded offer this while others are
just a bit too simple or too time
consuming to really effectively pull
this off the difficulty in designing
good levels is also impacted by the fact
that there's only one type of enemy mech
in the game and it always has the same
stats having weaker and stronger enemies
to choose from would have given me a lot
more freedom in how i design my levels
since as is i can't vary the number of
mechs that a player faces at any one
time too much without making the levels
too easy or too hard and since you can
always take time to heal it means that
levels with multiple isolated encounters
really just become slogfest as the last
level in the game unfortunately
demonstrates
so i touched really briefly on ai
previously but i'm going to dive into
that a little bit deeper now and explain
how that's set up the ai in lmx is
pretty simple but fairly effective for
what it is the only major flaw with it
is that there's no coordination among
enemy mechs which is the main thing i
think would help improve it and make it
more interesting without coordination
though i was able to get by with just an
ai node on each mech that can be used by
the mechs that need it and ignored by
the player's mix having an ai node on
every mech could also be used to provide
suggestions to a player about
potentially effective moves though that
was obviously completely out of scope
for the jam i think it could be a nice
option to have a larger scale project as
for the actual decision making it really
just comes down to this if an enemy mech
is next to a player punch them otherwise
move towards a tile adjacent to the
closest player mech then perform a melee
or ranged attack if within range for
either with the preference given to
melee attacks since they are stronger
lastly if there's no other viable action
to take just repair not much to it but
it works pretty effectively as this game
is neither a cakewalk nor brutally
unfair if i had coordination among mechs
it'd be great to have some enemies focus
on ranged attacks others focus on melee
and some focus on flanking the player or
otherwise trying to get them to move in
a certain direction or the split the
group up so that's kind of the direction
i would go if i was going to expand on
the ai further
so lastly let's talk audio starting with
the soundtrack the song for this jam is
pretty simple with bass and drums
driving the song and a few synthesizers
laid on top to fill everything out as i
usually do for game jams i focused on
making a short loop that wouldn't just
completely drive the player crazy that
you're repeating over and over and over
i like to accomplish this by not having
any drastic changes in the melody or
composition and also not having any sort
of lead instrument mixed too strongly
and oftentimes i'll just exclude any
sort of lead instrumentation altogether
that funky interlude or crunchy guitar
solo sounds cool the first five or even
10 times through but it ends up making
it really obvious when the music is
looping and eventually it just becomes
grating on the ears so the soundtrack to
lmx stays at a constant level of energy
and no instruments ever come in or out
of the mix not the most exciting way to
compose but at least you just kind of
start to ignore the music after a while
as opposed to wincing every time the
loop starts over for sound effects i had
a hard time finding anything online i
liked so i decided to just make it all
myself there's a bit of processing on
each sound effect to do things like add
some saturation and positive harmonics
make some eq adjustments maybe add a
little bit of reverb and echo but
otherwise the effects consist of this
the flamethrower effect is the tried and
true method of just blowing into the
microphone when you need a flame or kind
of explosive sound effect
the water effect is just a running
faucet
the gunshot of the pistol is just a
snare drum which ended up not mixing
very well on top of the music so that
was a bit of a misstep
the punching sound effect is an
electronic snare and clap combined
together to just give a nice smacking
sound
the lightning attack is crinkling
aluminum foil as the lead-up static
charge followed by the sound of me
hitting the garage door with my fist
synthesizers create the sound effects
for both repairing and dying
and hitting the ground either upon death
or when moving is me hitting my office
chair with my fist with a little bit of
a kick drum mixed in underneath to make
it more rumbly
and i'm not going to say that these are
the greatest sound effects in the world
but i think they're fairly solid
considering they're pretty humble
sources and so i would highly encourage
the viewer to try and make their own
sound effects sometime and see what they
can get out of it using techniques like
this and if you're not sure how to make
something just give it a google i do
that all the time there are entire
websites and forums dedicated to the art
of foley and sound effect creation and
so you're sure to find some options that
are feasible for you
and that is a pretty in-depth look at
how i made lmx in only two weeks time
overall i'm pretty happy with how the
game turned out and it's definitely a
pretty big milestone for me to tackle 3d
and tactics in only two weeks time
there's definitely a lot of room for
improvement with this game but i feel
like i have a much clearer idea of what
this process and overall system design
will need to look like for a future
project than when i started now that
i've gone ahead and done it once and
hopefully you have a clearer idea of how
to make a game like this yourself thanks
for watching